A Guide to the Papers of the Randolph Family of Edgehill and Wilson Cary Nicholas,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Wilson Cary Nicholas Papers
    - 1818 April 11 W[illiam] Jones to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses problems being experienced in the banking industry and the need to preserve specie, curtail loans, and call in old loans, 4 pages (Box-folder 3:37)
    - 1818 April 26 Wilson Cary Nicholas to William Jones, draft, discusses the miscommunications between the state banks and the Bank of the United States and his conversations with Doctor [John] Brockenbrough, president of the Bank of Virginia, and [Benjamin] Thatcher, head of the Farmer's Bank of Virginia, concerning the instructions coming from Jones, 4 pages (Box-folder 3:38)
    - 1818 April 29 J[ames] A. Buchanan to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], discusses the issues of bank credits and whether the Bank of the United States was financially stable. Explains why there is a clamor against the banks. Indicates that he will try to ensure that the recipient receives his loan to Mr. Patterson, 4 pages (Box-folder 3:39)
    - 1818 August 10 Wilson Cary Nicholas to "My Dear Sir," says it was not his wish that Clarke should have gone to Goochland if he did not want to and that he wants Clarke to serve Nicholas at Warren the next year, 2 pages (Box-folder 3:40)
    - 1818 August 17 M. Moore to Wilson Cary Nicholas, mentions his expectations of a fine tobacco crop this year and discusses the purchase of farmlands—prices, acreage, and type, 3 pages (Box-folder 3:41)
    - 1818 August 22 Wilson Cary Nicholas to W[illiam] Jones, draft, discusses the general opinion that the recent policies and directives coming out of the Bank of the United States, intentionally or not, will crush the state banks and tries to come up with ways to avoid that, 2 pages (Box-folder 3:42)
    - 1818 September 05 Thomas Marshall to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses improvements in farming techniques, his farmland and its successes and failures, 3 pages (Box-folder 3:43)
    - 1818 September 17 John Nicholas to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], informs Wilson of the upcoming visit of John's son, George, who is sickly and traveling to Virginia in hopes that it will benefit his health, 2 pages (Box-folder 3:44)
    - 1818 [December?] 17 Peggy Nicholas to Jane [Mrs. T. Jefferson] Randolph, indicates her surprise and displeasure that Patt was beaten for misbehavior. Mentions the visits of Ellen and Virginia [Randolph] with Jane; Continues to fill in on the gossip of the town, especially gossip concerning the wooing of the younger girls and their eventual coming-outs, 2 pages (Box-folder 3:45)
    - 1819 May 17 Benjamin Vaughan to Wilson Cary Nicholas, inquires whether Nicholas has read or heard of the Treatise on Rivers and Torrents with the method of regulating their course or an essay on navigable canals, both by Paolo Frisi (1728-1784), a Barnabite monk, and recommends them to Nicholas as beneficial for anyone interested in Richmond. Suggests that a Book Society should be established for the sharing of books and discussions of them, 4 pages (Box-folder 3:46)
    - 1819 May 20 John Hollins to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], asks Nicholas to "commit it to the flames," after reading his letter discussing the removal of Mr. McCulloh as cashier and the distressing financial conditions of the banks, 2 pages (Box-folder 3:47)
    - 1819 August 10,11 Wilson Cary Nicholas to William Wirt; with Wirt's reply on the same letter. Nicholas sends through several questions concerning the issues surrounding the banking situation in America and bonds, hoping his answers will help him decide which debts to forbid the payment of. Wirt answers the questions on the same letter, returning both to Nicholas, 4 pages (Box-folder 3:48)
    - 1819 August 16 G. L[awson] Nicholas to his uncle, Wilson Cary Nicholas, sends a parcel of clothing for his father, from Geneva, and asks for prompt payment as to keep his credit good. Also G. L. indicates that his father's health continues to be poor and is getting worse, 1 page (Box-folder 3:49)
    - 1819 October 28 William H. Cabell to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], considers it unsafe and unwise to enter into any kind of agreement with [Joseph?] Darmsdatt because it would hurt his credit. Continues to discuss why a protest would have destroyed his credit at the U.S. Bank and the Farmers Bank, and that he is pleased that he used the injunction that Chancellor Green gave him to prevent the protest, 2 pages (Box-folder 3:50)
    - 1819 November 03 Lewis Nicholas to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], encloses a letter from Mr. Edward Garland of Goochland and asks Nicholas to respond on behalf of himself as well, 2 pages (Box-folder 3:51)
    - 1819 November 17 William H. Cabell to Wilson Cary Nicholas, promises to remain silent about the changes of the terms made by the United States Bank since the first proposition was made by Nicholas to them and he discusses the financial arrangements made by them in regard to his debt in detail. Continues to discuss agricultural pursuits and mentions the editorial remarks of Roane in the Intelligencer, 3 pages (Box-folder 3:52)
    - 1819 November 25 P[hilip] N[orbonne] Nicholas to Wilson Cary Nicholas, mentions several suits against Nicholas on the docket and urges him to be present in court so that he can take the oath of insolvency, 3 pages (Box-folder 3:53)
    - 1819 December 24 Joseph C. Cabell to Wilson Cary Nicholas, apologizes for his delayed response, describing his wife's near fatal infection as a reason why he had not responded sooner. Reassures him that Doctor [John Augustine] Smith will not press his debt to the College [of William and Mary?] but will be satisfied with the interest. Asks about Nicholas's opinion of the book on canals which he lent him before, 1 page (Box-folder 3:54)
    - 1819 December 29 Wilson Cary Nicholas to Bernard Peyton, with fragment [in WCN's hand?], discusses the buying and selling of pork. Continues to discuss more financial and speculative issues, with Nicholas refusing to participate in a proposal that Peyton had put forth, 3 pages and a fragment (Box-folder 3:55)
    - 1820 January 13 William H. Cabell to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses his travel plans and his inability to visit Nicholas on his way to Richmond because he will be traveling with his wife. Discusses some legal issues including that "the answer of one defendant in Chancery can never be used as testimony against another defendant" and other rules of evidence and equity. Relays information that [Joseph?] Darmsdatt is dead and that Cabell does not know if he ever responded to his bill of injunction, 3 pages (Box-folder 3:56)
    - 1820 January 25 Dr. John Augustine Smith to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], discusses financial transactions, specifically the deposit of money from Mr. [Joseph?] Marx into Smith's account $477.82 and that he expected Mr. Marx to deposit, in total, $1100, 1 page (Box-folder 3:57)
    - 1820 February 03 William H. Cabell to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], discusses in detail his conversation with General Marshall about the financial affairs of Nicholas, and how his testimony could safely be admitted in court concerning the lawsuits against him. Cabell believes the "most favorable plan for the endorsers would be for suits to be immediately brought against them by the persons holding your paper" and "the only other advisable plan would be a suit in Chancery to perpetuate your testimony." Also discusses the impact of Mr. Giles suit upon Nicholas' own case, and mentions other suits that may exert an influence upon his affairs. He notes that the half year's interest on the $20,000 due the United States Bank will be due in three or four months, 4 pages (Box-folder 3:58)
    - 1820 February 04 J. Preston to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], discusses his present financial situation and reputation. Preston requests that his name be removed as an endorser to the recipient's note at the bank of Virginia, 2 pages (Box-folder 3:59)
    - 1820 February 20 Joseph Marx to Wilson Cary Nicholas, describes his recovery from a severe bout of gout. Informs Nicholas that he has been unable to sell his pork but is keeping it in the smoke house as he continues to try to sell it and lodge the sale amount to the credit of Dr. Smith. Mr. Christian, the bursar at the College of William and Mary, requested him to send the last receipts that he had from Mr. Coleman concerning the payment of his debt, because there appears to be a discrepancy., 2 pages (Box-folder 3:60)
    - 1820 October 05 William H. Cabell to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses the ongoing court trial, depositions, subpoenas, and other such legal issues concerning the financial affairs of Nicholas. General Marshall has "enclosed me a subpoena for you and also a commission and notice re questions that I would act for him as for myself - I have put them all, as well as my own papers into the hands of Mr. McClelland & requested him to do the needful,", 3 pages (Box-folder 3:61)
    - 1821 September 03 Robert Carter Nicholas to Major Wilson Cary Nicholas, Jr., in the process of negotiating the purchase of a small sugar plantation near [Bringiers, Louisiana?] responds to Wilson's question about his proposed purchase of all the slaves in [Heron Fenlow & Company?]. Nicholas urges him not to encumber himself with any that are old or infirm, such as Jonas, Baylor and Phoebe, because of the harshness of the climate would make them a source of expense rather than profit. He also discusses the slaves he brought with him that were not included in the purchases from Patterson & Cabell and his concerns about the propriety of bringing them with him, especially as concerns the Trustees. At the end of the letter, there is a list of the slaves currently with Robert C. Nicholas, their ages, and evaluation by Major Perkins, 3 pages (Box-folder 3:62)
    - 18[?] May 20 Bishop J. Madison to Wilson Cary Nicholas. The last two digits of the date are missing. The letter discusses the sale of some land to Nicholas belonging to [William and Mary College] for which there is no other encumbrance, about which the Visitors had questions, 1 page (Box-folder 3:63)
    - [?] June 08 Mary Nicholas to Wilson Cary Nicholas, [Jr.?], discusses goods that Mary wants Wilson to purchase for her that she would rather not purchase at Heron's Store. Also discusses travel plans, 3 pages (Box-folder 3:64)
    - [?] September 05 N[elson] Nicholas to Wilson Cary Nicholas, authorizes Wilson Nicholas to pay Samuel S. Nicholas the money that is due to Nelson Nicholas personally as well as the money that accrues to Nelson from the will of Mrs. Fairfax, 1 page (Box-folder 3:65)
    - N.D. Wilson Cary Nicholas to General Samuel Smith, draft. Although there is no date, the letter likely was written between 1818 and 1820 (the time between Nicholas's retirement from political office and death). The letter address Nicholas's failing financial means and his request for help since he has been unable to sell his property. He believes his land holdings are worth around $100,000 and his total estate at around $330,000, 4 pages (Box-folder 3:66)
    - N.D. [Mary Nicholas?] to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], needs eight or ten pounds in money and also sends her request for pork, 150 bushels of coal, two gallons of wine, two and a half yards of linen, and tea, 1 page (Box-folder 3:67)
    - N. D. Wilson Cary Nicholas to [ ? ], 3 draft fragments. All drafts are from after 1799 when Wilson's brother George passed away. The letters discusses the future of George's family and their financial prospects. Touched by the fact that General Samuel Smith will also be concerned in the future of the family. Expresses disbelief that the creditors would push so hard on a widowed family, 8 pages (Box-folder 3:68)
    - N.D. Wilson Cary Nicholas to Samuel Smith and James Morrison, three letter fragments from after 1799 when Wilson's brother George passed away. The letters discuss the division of George's property and how to best support his children. Mostly deals with financial business and possible solutions to the difficulties posed by the distance and the money, 10 pages (Box-folder 3:69)
    - N.D. Doctor [Charles] Everett to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses financial business and the need for Nicholas to pay his bills in full so that Everett has the money needed to fund a young man in college, 3 pages (Box-folder 3:70)
    - N.D. Joshua Fry [grandson of Joshua Fry (1700-1754)?] to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], discusses financial business concerning his son, touching briefly on obligations to Dr. Everett and Mr. Divers. Also mentions the purchase of slaves, 2 pages (Box-folder 3:71)
    - N.D. Wilson Cary Nicholas to [ ? ], draft fragment, discusses some financial business related to George Nicholas's estate (so after 1799) and General Samuel Smith, 4 pages (Box-folder 3:72)
    - N.D. John Nicholas to [Wilson Cary Nicholas], expresses gratitude for Wilson and other's concerns for his health in the past weeks. Indicates that with a continued and careful remedy that he is slowly getting better and describes how Mr. and Mrs. Rose have been of all help to him in this process, 4 pages (Box-folder 3:73)
    - N.D. Wilson Cary Nicholas to [ ? ], draft, expresses gratitude for the receiver's kind feelings over the last weeks which have been difficult and have presented numerous problems, 2 pages (Box-folder 3:74)
    - N.D. James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses Colonel Owings's refusal to pay the rest of his debt to General Smith which, Morrison admits, is less than he originally calculated, 2 pages (Box-folder 3:75)
    - N.D. Dabney Carr to Wilson Cary Nicholas, indicates that he is sending the balance that he owes Nicholas after deducting the sheriff's ticket, 1 page (Box-folder 3:76)
    - N.D. James Morrison to Wilson Cary Nicholas, fragment, mentions members involved in the Burr conspiracy, including Wilkinson and Blennerhassett, discusses some financial business and asks about Margaretta who Nicholas did not mention in his last letter, 2 pages (Box-folder 3:77)
    - N.D. M. Jones to Wilson Cary Nicholas, corrects a former business transaction on the copies of Nicholas's brothers letter to be sent to 19 gentlemen and to be kept by Nicholas, 1 page (Box-folder 3:78)
    - N.D. Description of Wilson Cary Nicholas in unidentified hand, fragment, provides a short description of Nicholas's merits as a politician and speaker. Written in past tense indicating that either Nicholas is leaving some sort of political office or has passed away, 1 page (Box-folder 3:79)
    Subseries B: Financial, Legal, and Miscellaneous Papers
    - 1765 March 12 Commission to appoint Robert Carter Nicholas power of attorney for William Dunlop and James Montgomery (Box-folder 3:80)
    - 1767 October 31 Three Bills of Exchange for money to be paid to Doctor Thomas Walters by Andrew Cochrane and William Cunninghame (Box-folder 3:81)
    - 1769 Lottery Ticket, signed by William Harris (Box-folder 3:82)
    - 1770 March 10 Invoice for entire list of goods purchased by John Norton for Robert C. Nicholas. Includes a Bill a Landing for these goods (Box-folder 3:83)
    - 1770 Receipts, thirteen total, for various goods purchased by John Norton. Goods include: nutmeg, pimento, cloves, mace, buttons, silk, nails, broad cloth, great coats, chamber pots, wash basins, and woolens. Purchased from John Middleditch, Thomas Nixon, James Sharp, Mauduit Wright, Robert Gosling, Benjamin Martin, Walter Humphrey, and Thomas Ainsley (Box-folder 3:84)
    - 1770 - 1771 Account of Robert C. Nicholas with John Norton & Sons (Box-folder 3:85)
    - 1770 -1771 Account of Robert C. Nicholas with John Norton & Sons (Box-folder 3:86)
    - 1771 July 18 Bill of Exchange for money to John Norton's private account (Box-folder 3:87)
    - 1771 December 31 Invoice for goods purchased by John Norton for Robert C. Nicholas (Box-folder 3:88)
    - 1771 Three Bills of Lading for goods shipped between John Norton and Robert C. Nicholas (Box-folder 3:89)
    - 1771 Receipts, two total, for goods purchased by John Norton (Box-folder 3:90)
    - 1772 April 28 Bill of account, Norton and Son to Thomas Page (Box-folder 3:91)
    - 1772 April 30 Bill of lading for goods shipped by John Norton to Robert C. Nicholas (Box-folder 3:92)
    - 1772 Three Bills of Exchange from Robert Carter Nicholas (Box-folder 3:93)
    - 1772 Two Invoices for goods purchased and shipped by John Norton for Robert Carter Nicholas (Box-folder 3:94)
    - 1786 April14 List of books purchased by Mr. Jeffries from J. Lackington Bookseller (London), written on the back of a broadside from J. Lackington (Box-folder 3:95)
    - 1787 October 06 Bill of Sale for 52,803 acres of land in Montgomery County, Virginia, to Wilson Cary Nicholas (Box-folder 3:96)
    - 1788 April 02 Receipt for Payment by Wilson Cary Nicholas of debt owed John Ambler by Robert C. Nicholas (Box-folder 3:97)
    - 1789 January 18 Promissory Note, for money owed George and Wilson Cary Nicholas by John Nicholas (Box-folder 3:98)
    - 1790 September 15 Indenture, made between Edward Carter, Charles Lilbourn Lewis, Howell Lewis, and Edward Moore, a majority of the Trustees for the town of Milton, and William D. Meriwether and Nicholas M. Lewis of the County of Albemarle (Box-folder 3:99)
    - 1791 December 09 Seven Geographical Lottery Tickets (Box-folder 3:100)
    - 1791 Receipt, signed by Wilson Cary Nicholas; Received by Jacob Kinney (Box-folder 3:101)
    - 1794 February 10 "A List of Land Office treasury warrants received of…Wilson Cary Nicholas by the hand of Mr. Jacob Kinney." (Box-folder 3:102)
    - 1794 April 08 Receipt, for Land Office Warrants from Wilson Cary Nicholas in name of William Patterson; signed by [Hudson?] Martin (Box-folder 3:103)
    - 1795 March 14 Indenture, for the sale of 791 acres of land in Albemarle County to Wilson Cary Nicholas by John Harris (Box-folder 3:104)
    - 1796 Two financial papers of Wilson Cary Nicholas (Box-folder 3:105)
    - 1796 August 27 Bill documenting the sale of the use of a patent granted to Wilson Cary Nicholas, signed by Evan Evans on behalf of Oliver Evans, who invented and perfected improvements for the manufacturing of grain into flour (OS Edgehill-Randolph Box)
    - 1796 November 16 Receipt, paid by Peter Heiskell for his policy with the "Mutual Assurance Society against Fire on Buildings" (Box-folder 3:106)
    - 1797 June 02 Promissory Note, signed by George Peyton, promissory to pay J.B. Nicholas (Box-folder 3:107)
    - 1797 October 17 Receipt for taxes paid by John Coles on his carriage, signed by Matthew Rodes, Collector of the Revenue (Box-folder 3:108)
    - 1798 January 01 Indenture, for sale of land to Wilson Cary Nicholas by Joshua and Peachey Fry (Box-folder 4:1)
    - 1798 February 05 Land grant, signed by Governor James Wood, granting land in Amherst County to Wilson Cary Nicholas. (OS Edgehill-Randolph Box)
    - 1799 April 23 Indenture, for sale of land in Albemarle County by Wilson Cary Nicholas to William Walker. (OS Edgehill-Randolph Box)
    - 1799 May 11 Last Will and Testament of George Nicholas (Copy) (Box-folder 4:2)
    - 1799 September 06 Last Will and Testament of Wilson Cary Nicholas (Box-folder 4:3)
    - [c. 1799] Account settlement made from estate of George Nicholas for debts owed Wilson Cary Nicholas (Box-folder 4:4)
    - [c. 1799] Account settlement made from Estate of Colonel G[eorge] Nicholas for debts owed Wilson Cary Nicholas (Box-folder 4:5)
    - [c. 1800] Statement of account owed various people by estate of George Nicholas, signed by J[ames] M[orrison] (Box-folder 4:6)
    - 1801 May 30 Two receipts for "Arms and Accoutrements," one delivered by Wilson Cary Nicholas to Major John Jordan, the other delivered by David [Wharton?] to John Jordan, 1 st Battalion 47 th Regiment (Box-folder 4:7)
    - 1801 May 31 Indenture, for purchase of land on Green Mountain by Wilson Cary Nicholas from John Nicholas (Box-folder 4:8)
    - 1802-1803 Record of 'Sales of Negroes' by [Estate of George Nicholas?] to approximately thirty-five different parties, including columns for time of payment, names of Negroes sold, purchasers names, and amount of sale (Box-folder 4:9)
    - 1802 September 21 Financial Contract between Wilson Cary Nicholas and Samuel Smith (Box-folder 4:10)
    - 1803 May 23 A settlement of account between Wilson Cary Nicholas and the estate of George Nicholas, signed by the auditors, Cuthbert Banks and John [Postlethwait?] (Box-folder 4:11)
    - 1803 September 13 Land Grant signed by Governor John Page, giving land in Albemarle County to Wilson Cary Nicholas (OS Edgehill-Randolph Box)
    - 1803-1804 Invoice, for goods bought by Wilson Cary Nicholas from Liston Temple (Box-folder 4:12)
    - 1804 July 01 Bill of Account, for money owed Samuel Smith by Wilson Cary Nicholas (Box-folder 4:13)
    - 1804 November 01 Indenture, for sale of land in Albemarle County to Benjamin Childers by Wilson Cary Nicholas (Box-folder 4:14)
    - 1805 March 02 Receipt, for notes turned over to Wilson Cary Nicholas by Edmund Randolph to serve as payment for the latter's debts (Box-folder 4:15)
    - 1805 September 07 Waiver of debt owed Edmund Randolph by Wilson Cary Nicholas (Box-folder 4:16)
    - 1805 September 07 Transfer of title for property of Edmund Randolph to Wilson Cary Nicholas for security against a slave sale by Edmund Randolph to Wilson Cary Nicholas (Box-folder 4:17)
    - 1806 February 28 Wilson Cary Nicholas's last will and testament (Box-folder 4:18)
    - 1806 June 07 Invoice, for goods sold Wilson Cary Nicholas by Taylor and Brown (Box-folder 4:19)
    - 1807-1808 Transaction Notes between Wilson Cary Nicholas and Reuben and James Lindsay for sale of land and shares (Box-folder 4:20)
    - 1808 May 24 List of Wilson Cary Nicholas's tobacco weights, signed by Mosby Young (Box-folder 4:21)
    - 1809 March 22 Bill of Exchange, from Isaac A. Coles to Baguenault & Company, Paris (Box-folder 4:22)
    - 1809-1810 Invoice, for goods purchased from James Leitch by Wilson Cary Nicholas (Box-folder 4:23)
    - 1811 September 05 Indenture, for sale of Albemarle County land by Wilson Cary Nicholas to Robert Morrison (Box-folder 4:24)
    - 1798-1812 Bill of Account for Wilson Cary Nicholas with James Morrison (Box-folder 4:25)
    - 1812 September 03 Transfer of Title to an Annuity from Ann and Lewis Sanders to Nelson Nicholas (Box-folder 4:26)
    - 1812 December 11 Financial Document concerning the value of a lot on Cary Street, [Richmond, Virginia] belonging to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?] and the Nicholas family (Box-folder 4:27)
    - [1812?] Wilson Cary Nicholas's Notes concerning [the relationship of the United States and Great Britain?] (Box-folder 4:28)
    - 1815 - 1816 Invoice, for goods purchased by Wilson Cary Nicholas from Sewell Osgood (Box-folder 4:29)
    - 1815 Invoice, for goods purchased from Ed. Hallam by Wilson Cary Nicholas (Box-folder 4:30)
    - 1815 June-August Invoice, for goods purchased by Wilson Cary Nicholas from Nelson and Drew (Box-folder 4:31)
    - 1815 -1816 Notes, between Wilson Cary Nicholas and Mr. Archer, concerning thirteen orders for bushels of coal (Box-folder 4:32)
    - 1815 December 18 Invoice, for goods bought by J. James, Jr. from William J. Coles (Box-folder 4:33)
    - 1815 December 19 Invoice for goods bought by Wilson Cary Nicholas from Carter H. Drew (Box-folder 4:34)
    - 1815-1816 Bill of Account, for services done for Wilson Cary Nicholas by James Morrison (Box-folder 4:35)
    - 1816 January 16 Promissory Note, for $462.40 owed Samuel Smith Nicholas by John N. Nicholas; also signed by Wilson Cary Nicholas (Box-folder 4:36)
    - 1816 January 19 Invoices, for coal bought by Wilson Cary Nicholas from William Archer and D. M. Thornton & Company (Box-folder 4:37)